We are kicking off this evening
a week-long celebration
of a landmark event,
which is the golden anniversary
of the Allerton Conference on Communication, Control,
and Computing.
For those of you who have
been regular attendees
at the Allerton Conference
for many years
and for some probably Allerton is special place
in your career,
having presented
your first paper
or second paper in your career at the Allerton Conference,
and I know that there are
many of you out there.
For those of you for whom this
is the very first
Allerton Conference,
an-and for all conference attendees and for our guests,
this is a historic moment.
It's a celebration
of a multi-disciplinary scientific meeting
which was launched 50 years ago on November 15, 1963
with vision and
incredible foresight.
It was the brainchild
of Mac Van Valkenburg
who, together with Joe Cruz,
co-chaired the first conference 50 years ago.
Bill Perkins, eh, who is here,
ehht, and, eh,
he was also involved
in the initial discussions
and planning of the conference,
and I believe he is the only one in this room
who has witnessed that historic event 50 years ago.
The creatives' vision was,
as articulated by Mac and Joe in the forward to the proceedings
of that first conference.
That vision was to provide an
opportunity for researchers
to present their fresh new results
in a dynamic growing field
and to bring researchers in
different disciplines together
to cultivate cross-fertilization of ideas.
And this was right on target.
And this far-reaching vision
of its founders is still
the guiding light
at Allerton 50 years later.
It's-it's one of the longest running conferences
at least that I'm aware
of in the systems area,
and it's one
of the most prestigious.
It's perhaps the only longest
running conference
that has never changed
its venue.
From the very beginning, it has been held at the Allerton House
in Monticello, Illinois.
Only a minor adjustment was made
in going from the first to the second Allerton Conference
in 1964,
which was to move the date from the chilly mid November
to late September, which was September 28th through the 30th.
That's when the-the second Allerton Conference was held,
so that the attendees can enjoy the beautiful fall weather
at the Allerton grounds,
and it looks like,
at least some of the days
we'll have that beautiful weather with us this year also.
I'm told, eh, I'm not sure to what extent that it is a fact,
but, eh, Mac actually wanted to hold the first, eh, conference
in October,
the first week in October
because that coincided,
would have coincided
with his birth date,
which was October 5th.
But the Allerton House was not
available at the time,
and I'm told
that was the reason why
it was pushed to
November the 15th.
But then immediately
the following year,
it was brought back
to the first week
or the last week in September,
and since then
it has always been held
either the last week
in September
or the first week in October.
The conference has evolved
over the years
in parallel to the developments in the fields of communication,
control, and computing,
and in fact it has at times influenced, impacted, and shaped
the evolutions in those fields.
Some of the very early results,
which then became landmarks
in these fields,
were presented
at the Allerton Conference.
To share with you some numbers,
in 1963,
at the very first conference
there were
11 technical sessions,
3 general or what we now call plenary sessions,
they were not called
that way at the time,
with 62 individual presentations involving 84 authors.
The proceedings of that
inaugural meeting
was edited by Joe Cruz,
and it comprised 780 pages.
And here I have actually a copy of that very first proceedings
and it is in such good shape,
50 years later.
[laughing]
And the, and the proceedings in the intervening years
have always looked like this.
Nothing has changed.
And the, eh, today, as compared with those initial numbers,
49 years later,
we have in the program
this week, 65 sessions,
344 individual presentations,
and have almost 500 authors, maybe even over 500 authors,
are involved in these papers which will be presented here.
So it's a, it's a major growth,
but we are limited by the size of the Allerton House,
so don't expect
those numbers to grow,
to double within the next even, uh, 10 years.
So talking about
the celebrations,
this, eh, golden anniversary of the Allerton Conference
is not the only important anniversary on our campus today.
Today is also the exact,
to the day,
first year anniversary of our chancellor, Phyllis Wise,
taking on the stewardship
of our campus.
We are delighted and honored
to have her here with us
this evening to share with us this important moment
and to officially open
this kick-off event
for the golden anniversary.
Chancellor Wise also holds
the position
of Vice President
of the University of Illinois,
and as CEO of our campus
she is responsible for all financial programs,
campus policies, and priorities with the mission of insuring
a transformative,
educational experience
for America's next generation
of leaders.
She has held, eh, faculty and
administrative appointments
at the University of Washington,
at the University
of California at Davis
and Kentucky, eh, prior to joining here, eh, Illinois.
Eh, her research career
has focused on issues
concerning women's health
and gender based biology.
She is a Fellow of AAAS
and a member of the
National Academy of Sciences
Institute of Medicine.
Please join me in welcoming
Vice President and Chancellor, Phyllis Wise,
to the podium, to open
this golden anniversary.
[applause]
(Phyllis Wise)
Somebody took good care
of these proceedings
from 50 years ago.
It's a real honor to be here
in this overflowing room.
I wonder whether
we're in fire code,
but that's, that's okay.
I won't say anything,
if you don't.
Um, it is truly an honor
to be here
to, uh, welcome you to
the 50th anniversary celebration
of this wonderful conference with such a long
and strong history.
Y'know, um,
when I got this position
I tried really hard to, uh,
do a lot of homework
on the University of Illinois
to learn about
my new academic home,
and I must admit I did not come across the Allerton Conference
so I must not have done
homework enough to realize
what a rich tradition was really started 50 years ago.
Um, this conference
really is an illustration of,
uh, what can happen
at a great university
with a 145 year history.
Uh, the-the story that you just told, Professor Baser-Basar,
and, uh, what I'm learning tonight about all of this,
is truly amazing.
I think it's wonderful that it
started out at Allerton
and it continues
to be at Allerton.
I think it's wonderful to know
that sometimes traditions
should be carried on
because they hav-are part of
the richness of the experience.
Um, you know, I-I just want to add tonight that, uh,
I'm sure that this is the beginning of the next 50 years
of this conference,
and though it won't get larger in terms of number,
that that is actually
a good thing
because sometimes the intimacy that you gather from having
only a few hundred people
cannot be replicated
when you let it grow
into thousands and thousands
of people at the same time.
So I wish you the very
best in this conference.
I am honored to be here to
welcome you to it
and I wish you the richest of ca-discussions
and, and, um, new discoveries being discussed here.
Thank you very
much for having me.
[clapping]
(male)
Now that we have
the official opening of the confernece, Allerton Conference
we can, uh, eh,
continue with the program,
and, eh, and we have a very distinguished, eh, eh, speaker,
eh, to, uh, eh, for this, eh, kick-off evening,
and-and this is
something special.
Allerton Conference,
for those of you who have attended in the past,
has always been for three days
and all events were held
out in Monticello,
and because of this
50th anniversary
we decided to, eh, have
a kick-off event here on campus
and so that we can attract, uh, people who maybe normally
would not have
gone out to Allerton.
And, eh, and, and we wanted to pick someone, uh,
who is, uh, who will talk to the importance of this occasion.
And, eh, I'm very pleased, eh, eh, to, eh, have, eh,
Karl Astrom from
Lund University of Sweden,
eh, to be the keynote speaker
or the Jubilee Lecturer
this evening.
Eh, he is a world renown control
scientist and engineer
and educator,
and I can take
a full hour, actually,
to talk about his accomplishments,
his impact on the field,
not only on the control field but-but-but across the board
and, eh, eh, communications, eh, and-and computing,
those that-that are really
the topics
and areas that are covered Aller-at
the Allerton Conference.
So let me say just a-a few brief, eh, words on, uh,
Karl's background and-and
some of his achievements.
As I said, I won't be
able to cover everything.
He was educated at
the Royal Institute of Technology in Stockholm.
During his studies, he worked on
inertial navigation
for Research Institute
of National Defense.
After working for IBM research
for five years,
he was appointed Professor of the Chair of Automatic Control
at Lund Institute of Technology, or Lund University,
where he established
a new department.
From 2000 'til 2010
he was a professor
at the University of California in Santa Barbara,
and he is currently back at
Lund University
as a, as a senior professor.
Uh, he has broad interest in control including,
stochastic control, modeling, system identification,
adaptive control,
computer control,
and computer-aided
control engineering.
He is listed in the ISI,
ISA Highly Cited
and-and he has
the Adarsh number three.
For those of you who don't
know what that means,
ask your neighbor,
but after the lecture.
And, uh, two,
he has seven books,
and two of these books
have received the prestigious Harold Chestnut Textbook Prize
from the International Federation of Automatic Control.
And one of his papers on
self-tuning control,
which is very well known,
very well cited,
which was co-authored
with Wittenmark,
eh, again from Lund University,
was selected for the IEEE book on control theory.
This was the millennium, eh, book on Control Theory,
25 Seminal Papers,
eh, covering the period
1932 and 1981.
There were only 25 papers that
were picked, eh, er-eh, out of,
from a pool of thousands
of papers,
and-and this was one of those.
Eh, he has several patents,
and one of them for automatic tuning of PID controllers,
which he holds jointly
with-with Hagglund,
eh, and that has led
to substantial
industrial production.
Eh, Karl is a member
of the Royal Society,
Royal Swedish Academy of Engineering, Sciences,
and the Royal Swedish Academy
of Sciences.
He is a foreign member
of the U.S. National Academy
of Engineering,
the Russian Academy of Sciences,
and the Hungarian
Academy of Sciences.
He is a Fellow of IFAC,
a life Fellow of IEEE,
and he has received many honors,
among them
six honorary doctorates,
eh, the 1985 Oldenburger Medal from the, eh,
American Society of Mechanical Engineers, ASME.
The 1987 Quazza Medal from the Information Federat-eh,
International Federation of Automatic Control, IFAC,
and-and which is the highest medal that organization bestows
on, eh, ehm, eh, scientists and engineers in the control field.
The 1990 IEEE Control Systems Award he is a recipient of,
and-and also the 1993
IEEE Medal of Honor,
which is the highest award
of IEEE
which is the largest engineering organization in the world,
and the 2002 Great Gold Medal
of the Royal Swedish Academy
of Engineering,
and in 2003 he was inducted, uh,
into the Process Control
of-of Fame.
and, uh, please join me
in welcoming Karl
to deliver the Jubilee Lecture.
[applause]
(Karl)
Thank you very much, Tamer.
I should also tell the students,
sitting there in the back,
there are a couple
of seats up front.
Don't be shy, but step forward
and use these seats, please.
Um, it's certainly a great honor for me to speak
on this fantastic location
of the celebration
of the Allerton Conference.
So, I would like to
thank you very much
for inviting me to do this.
And, em, Tamer asked me to give a broad picture of control,
and I was brave enough
to take this picture.
There should actually be
a sub-line here saying,
"a personal reflection."
So remember what I'm saying here are my personal views.
They're certainly
not universal truth.
So, eh, control has been around for a long time,
but it really started to grow in connection with the development
of the industries.
Eh, it was sometimes
an enabling technology,
but one didn't recognize that there were lots of similarities
between for example, process control, telecommunications,
flight control, etc.
And it became an engineering discipline in the 1940s,
eh, and it has been developing very, very rapidly.
And today we have lots
and lots of applications
and also some
very interesting challenges.
Eh, there have recently been a
couple of studies
of broad pictures of control.
For example, the IEEE
Control Systems Society
has published a book called The Impact of Control Technology,
which is available on the web,
and in connection with
the year eh-two, eh-2000
there were a couple
of books presented
that gave a perspective of engineering and control,
uh, in this century,
and I listed a few of them there
and we'll come back
to them later.
One thing,
that has been a hallmark
of the control community
is a solid foundation.
And I've always been wanting to
have an illustration of this
and by accident I found this
in Montreal this summer.
This beautiful building here
happens to be an insurance building in Montreal.
And you look at this beaut,
it was one of the most beautiful buildings in Montreal.
But this tower fell down
because the foundations
were not so good.
They had put in wooden pillars
in the ground
and then they started to rot.
So, what I'm saying here, even
if you have a beautiful house,
unless the foundations
are solid,
eh, it's gonna tumble down.
So I'm very proud to say
that this has been
a hallmark of control
and you will see this logo popping up here and there.
I've called control
the hidden technology.
Eh, it's widely used,
it's very successful,
it's seldom talked about
except when there's a disaster, you know.
When a reactor blows up,
when the airplane crashes.
And I've often
been wondering why.
And I think it's much easier to
talk about devices than ideas.
It's much easier to say,
will a computer fix that
than the ideas
that are behind it.
And also I think
we have something to blame ourselves for.
We have been very bad at
telling what control is
to our fellow scientists
and also, em, to our colleagues and to the general public.
Eh, so therefore,
I have advised our students,
this is something
that we have done badly
and you in the next generation now have to do it.
So I think Intel
did it very well
with this sort of Intel inside, y'know.
So we should have something
like Control inside.
So that would be one symbol.
And then we should remember, y'know,
to keep the foundations okay.
And if we do this, things would
be very well here in the future.
So what will I do now?
Well I have a very
simple outline.
I-its exactly follows the title.
The past, the present,
the future,
and then I will do
a little summary.
So now let's do the past.
Eh, control is a young field.
Ehm, it's a little bit older than the Allerton Conference.
Eh, and-em, eh, so it's useful
to think about this.
We are not matured, y'know.
We're a little bit more
than teenagers but barely.
Eh, there's been e-early use
of control in many fields.
In governors for machines,
in process controls,
in vehicle control,
and communication.
As I said before, people didn't
realize it was the same thing
until we got the Servomechanism
Theory around, say, 1940, 1950.
And this had
tremendous consequences.
Education on control spread
like wildfire
in all engineering education
and I think everybody would have been proud a-uh, about this.
But around 1960, y'know,
about the time the Allerton Conference started,
there was a paradigm shift.
And we got to tackle
the second phase in control
that I will talk a lot about.
And I think what we're
experience now
is the third phase.
And I'm not so sure about this
so that's why I put
a question mark over there.
So let's now do something.
Let's look at power generation.
Y'know, you start to
generate electric power
and if you were using AC
you wanted to generate it
with constant frequency.
The solution to this
was that you introduced a turbine controller
which is a classic watt
governor that was, eh,
y'know, these two wheels
start spinning around.
If they go-go, eh, if go fast,
you-you, eh, reduce
the amount of water
that's coming in, etc.
The side effect of this is that whenever you use feedback,
you run the risk of instability.
And that happened when people
started to experiment with this,
so you need it to have
stability theory.
And there were
a number of people,
that you can see
in the bottom of the slide
who contributed to this.
There you see from-from left to right you see Maxwell,
who actually wrote one
of the early papers
of analysis of control systems,
Routh, a British mathematician,
Stodola, a Swiss
turbine engineer,
Hurwitz, a sw-a Swiss mathematician,
Vyshnegradski, a Russian engineer, and Lyapunov.
So there was a whole lo-eh-slough of people
who were developing
stability theory.
Let's move to another
field, process control.
Typical problem was a chemical
process to keep temperatures,
to keep pressures,
etc. constant.
The solution to this
was the PID controller.
There were some
nice side effects.
We got an industrial
communication standard,
consisting of plastic tubes
of given dimensions
and the agreement that you should propagate signals
by pressures between
3 and 15 psi.
And then you had
standard instruments
and standard devices
that you connected.
Course with the day's
communication standard, eh,
it's not too good
and not too fast,
but at least it was a standard.
We also got two new rules
to tune the PID controllers.
Flight Control.
Question is how to fly?
And one reason that the Wright
Brothers succeeded
was that they
understood dynamics.
And they designed an airplane that was easy to maneuver
but was not terribly stable.
Many other people designed
stable airplanes
that were difficult to maneuver.
Em, a side effect
of this is that, em,
it's boring to sit there
and stabilize an airplane.
And you can see there on the
plane up here, em, there is, em,
Eh, Sperry's son
is sitting there
and they put an autopilot
on this plane
and, em, eh, th-th-the mechanic was walking on the wing
to introduce a perturbation
and you can see that it's
pretty close to the ground.
So i-in-in, around 1913
this autopilot
won the prize for the most stable airplane at, eh,
in Paris.
And I've taken this
from the Honeywell book.
In that they say,
"An interesting feature is
the proximity to the ground."
(laughing)
And down there on the left you can see the Wright Brothers
and then you can see,
em, eh, Minorsky
who was a ship engineer, eh, who was very heavily involved
in the interaction between stability and control.
Here's another field, telecommunications.
Em, the problem was how can you
communicate over long distances?
And to do this you
needed amplification.
So you needed to make
a good amplifier.
We are not talking
about 1920, 1930.
And their amp, the amplifying device at that time
was the electronic tube,
a pretty crummy device.
It gave you amplification,
but it was non-linear
and it had time
bearing characteristic.
And then we had some brilliant
people who we, eh,
at Bell Labs invented
the feedback amplifier.
So what did, eh,
it was done by Black.
And the idea was that,
how can you make a system out
a bad component?
And the-uh-the answer was
by using feedback
you can actually do this.
And you see this
calculation down here
for a feedback amplifier,
that, eh, if you, if-arrange a feedback in here,
you look at the-the gain.
It's essentially if k is
large, the gain is large.
These two terms disappeared
and essentially R2 over R1
which are passive component.
So that was the key idea
of the feedback amplifier.
Of course, again, people run
into stability problems.
Here they call it singing
because this amplifier
started to, y'know,
this sort of sound you had here in the beginning
with the microphone
and the loud speaker.
So therefore you had to do
stability theory
and there are two giants.
Bode, who I was told grew up
here in Urbana,
and, em, eh, his father was a professor here in
classics or languages,
and there were Harry Nyquist who grew up in Sweden.
Eh, the reason why feedback
is used so much
that that's a tremendous power.
You can make accurate system
from imprecise component
like you did
in electronic amplifiers.
You can reduce effects
of disturbances
and component variation
like you do in process control.
You can regulate, stabilize,
and shape behavior.
You're a fantastic properties.
So what are the drawbacks?
Drawback number one
is risk for instability.
And that's why stability has played such an important role
in control engineering.
Y'know, you really
have to know,
you have to know your enemies.
[laughing]
The other thing about feedback
is that you are feeding sensor noise into the system
so that noise will create
a lot of action
that you would like to avoid.
So these are the two drawbacks.
But, of course, if you look
to the advantages
we have a lot of positive things going for us.
So the scene of 1940 was
widespread use of control
in many fields
and I gave you examples of this.
I listed them there.
The similarities
were not realized.
So what it took to-to realize the similarities was essentially
the Second World War.
So during the Second World
War, what happened was that,
em, politicians realized
that science could have a major impact on the outcome of a war.
And here in United States
and in other places,
want organized laboratories around universities
which were going to develop the m-m-military tools,
the radar, etc.
And of course very prominent here in the United States
was the effort around MIT.
So I want to, gunsights,
radar, etc.
So the concepts were to use feedback and feedforward.
And what happened then is that
they brought in people
who had very different talents.
They brought in people,
for example,
who new about autopilots.
They brought in
people from Bell Labs.
They brought in people from
the process control industry.
And then people discovered
we have actually been doing
the same thing.
And then control emerged.
And, em, the, eh, design tools were block diagrams
and transfer functions.
The simulation tools
were analog simulation.
Implementation was again
that whenever you would have to build a controller you's,
you essentially using
analog techniques.
And at that time
there was a holistic view
of theory and applications.
So, essentially, the same groups
who were doing application,
were also doing theory.
Eh, here's a little picture
of servomechanism theory.
Eh, the picture on the left
illustrates, em,
the block diagram,
which is a very nice way
of abstracting away details
from a technical system.
The picture in the middle show a
hardware in the loop simulation
from the Saab Airplane Company
around 1952,
and you see an analog computer sitting there, on the right.
The theory was
Laplace transforms
and complex variables.
System concepts,
feedback, feedforward.
Design was frequency response,
a lot of graphical methods,
and then analog simulation
and analog implementation.
Here's one of the early books
on control.
The reason it's called
Servomechanism Theory.
And notice,
it's written by a professor
of physics from Purdue.
It's written by
an instrument engineer
from an instrument company,
Nathaniel Nichols,
and a first rate abstract mathematician, Ralph Phillips
from, eh, University
of Southern California.
Cert its conception,
control was multidisciplinary
with a strong footing
in mathematics,
a strong footing in physics,
and a strong footing
in instrumentation.
The consequences
of this were tremendous.
We were getting e-education of
control engineers, sort of.
Control courses
sprung up everywhere.
They came in different
departments, mechanical,
electric, sometimes
in civil engineering.
Eh, we got organizations where
the most prominent is IFAC,
International Federation
of Automatic Control,
was founded '57.
Eh, there was industrialization.
The company was
specializing on control.
Like Johnson Control,
like Honeywell.
We got journals
and we got conferences
and I think today, there's a control conference every week.
I think every subject
would have been proud of this,
and we are now come
roughly to 1960.
So, in 1960 I said we
had a paradigm shift.
And in my mind
the driver was a space race.
You know Sputnik came up 1957,
generated a fantastic
amount of activity.
Another thing that came
around were the computers.
So one started to use computers
to solve control,
to implement control systems
instead of using
analog computers.
And the first installation
was i-was in an oil refinery
in Texas in '59.
Eh, also it was discovered that the tools that were available
at the time, in 1960
were insufficient.
So what happened then,
we turned a lot to mathematics
to bring in, y'know,
new tools and new ideas.
There was a rapid growth
of s-subspecialties,
optimal control, stochastic control, nonlinear control, etc.
We also got computational tools.
Y'know, MATLAB today is a
successor of what was
developed at the time.
There was a very impressive
development of theory,
but the holistic view was lost.
Eh, I've sometimes
said at the time that, em,
there were many professors
of control
who had a platonic view
of control systems.
They talked a lot about them,
but they never touched them.
[laughing]
And, em, that illustrates, y'know, the, uh, lack of the
holistic view.
Eh, I'll give you a
couple of examples.
One of the most promising one-eh, p-prominent one
was optimal control theory.
Eh, it was built on-on, eh, classical results,
like by Hamilton and Euler.
And then we had Bellman who
developed dynamic programming,
direct descendant
of Hamilton and Jacobi.
We had Pontryagin,
who you can say,
his ideas were direct descendents
of Euler and Lagrange.
And today we have what you
call model predictive control.
A lot of this was driven
by the space race.
Y'know, you would like to
shoot up a heavy satellite
with a weak rocket,
you better do it
in the right way.
Eh, and here I just gave
two books,
one by Bellman
and one by Pontryagin.
Another very important
thing that happened
was the Kalman filtering.
And I put Wiener
right on the left
because Wiener filtering
was the predecessor.
In-in many senses a lot of the
machine was developed by him.
And then Kalman came along
and found very efficient ways
to filter signals
and he could
combine measurements
with mathematical models to
es-to do estimation.
So that's the basis
of the Kalman filtering.
Another thing is that we also
got a new structure
of the controller.
Instead of the controller
being a black box,
we now saw that the controller
should have a couple
of components,
a Kalman filter, here,
that receives all the
information from the process.
It generates, best
estimate of the state.
Then we have here a feedforward
generator that-that generates
both feedforward signal, that drives the system
where we would like it to go
and also desire-generates desired behavior of the state
and then we just do
state feedback up here.
So, that was something that we
got out of the Kalman's work
and the Kalman filtering.
We also got system
identification,
a methodology to get out mathematical models
from experiments.
This is data I made myself in a
paper factory in the early 60s.
We which-we, uh, wanted to know
how does a big factory
behave from input/output
and then you persuade the people
to let you change things
during production
and you measure important variables in the end.
And then based on this data
you, em, eh, you estimate
mathematical relations
between these ones.
And the typical idea is that
by-by doing better control
you can move closer to tolerances here
and you can save money.
So here's a tip, one of the first experiments we did
when we were controlling the thickness of paper accurately.
It was a project that IBM
was running together
with the Swedish paper mill.
Here's another area,
adaptive control.
Em, one of the things, eh, it actually came up, er,
from aerospace
because when airplanes
started to go supersonic,
the dynamics changed.
And then it was not enough
to have an autopilot
with fixed settings
so one tried to do an autopilot that could adjust itself
to changing flight conditions.
The early experiments
were not too successful.
There was a famous crash
on the X-15, for example.
So the field has been
going up and down
and has continued
to go up and down.
Eh, one of the things
I've been concerned with
was called
the self-tuning regulator.
Eh, there was a lot of
theory developed.
There were case studies.
Eh, I've given here
a couple of products
that I will skip
because of time.
I'll give you one
example, though.
A ship steering autopilot.
This was something
we developed from my lab
together with a local
shipyard in Kockums.
And when I Google this now,
the autopilot is still marketed by Northrop Grumman.
And here I gave you an example.
A typical autopilot
runs a PID controller,
and here you see
what is happening,
how the course is deviating
when you're running
in pretty bad weather
and here you see
what the rudder is doing.
When we switched on the adaptive
controller in here,
you see what happens to
the course deviations.
You don't have to do an analysis
to see that this is better.
The reason that the adaptive
controller can do it here,
it knows about waves
and it's trying to estimate
what the wave motion is.
And you can also see,
we are not using
larger rudder motions
than what you are doing
with the PID controller.
That's a little bit more
high frequency in here.
So I would say that this is a
very nice example of
adaptive control
that was done 30 years ago,
and the products are still here, here running.
One nice thing here is that you
know quite a bit about ships
so one can actual do a
physics-based initialization
of the system.
So if you know basic data
about the ship,
you can roughly figure out
what the initial parameters
are going to be.
Em, here's a special
subject I will take up.
Because in the early phase
of servomechanism,
people knew that there were limitations of control.
People knew that
time delays are bad.
instabilities are bad.
People know that
what we call zeros in the
right-half-plane, are bad.
When, em, the so-called modern
control theory came around
with Kalman filters
and state feedback,
these conditions somehow
did not show up,
if you looked upon the way people were looking about it.
So then people say,
eh, well, y'know,
maybe these limitations
are not so serious anyway.
And, eh, uh,
I attended conference
that were violent discussions,
y'know, between the people
who were advocating,
what was at the time called, modern control theory
and the classic guys.
The classic guys were saying
like this,
oh, time delays are limitations.
It must come into the theory.
Zeros in the right-half-planes
are very bad.
They must come in.
And then the guys sitting there
on the-the modern control say,
oh, y'know, you guys are stupid.
Y'know, you don't know
about matrixes,
calculations like this.
So we have this fantastic
robustness property, etc.
Well in the end,
so it was almost like
religious battles, y'know.
So instead of sitting down
and-and asking,
trying out what the problem was and resolving it,
y-you becam-you got
a religious fight
that lasted for several years.
So it took a long time
to figure this out.
And I'm very pleased to say that
eh, one of the first glimpses
of what was going on
was actually presented at the Allerton Conference
by this man here,
which is called George Zames,
in 1979.
Am I correct now?
Yes, 79.
So that was the first time
it came up that
there's probably something about the fundamental limitations
about time delays.
And then it took a while,
eh, but the, and of course what contributed to this
was that state space had a i-had infinite gain margin
and phase margin of 60 degrees.
Of course that had
to do with the fact
that you're measuring
all the state values.
When you do output feedback,
this is not at all true.
So then the field of robust
control came around,
and Youla, who was
very active here
from the first
Allerton Conference,
was one of the key
contributors to this.
And then there was a very
famous paper
that's called the four-author paper by John Doyle,
eh, Keith Glover, Khargonekar, and Bruce Francis.
I couldn't find a good picture
of Bruce Francis,
but he should be here.
[laughing]
And, em, it,
then it became very clear
that there are indeed fundamental limitations.
So, y'know, the classical guys
were right about this.
And also, eh, one figured out
the way to solve this.
Then, another thing
happened here in Illinois.
Eh, you recognize
our friend here?
And he had a colleague in France
called Pierre Bernhard,
and they said well,
it's all games.
See, in other words,
they formulated the robust control problem
as a game problem.
Nature is providing
the bad perturbations
and what you are doing is that you're playing against nature.
The very nice consequence
of this
is that it opened up the area
to do robust control
for nonlinear systems.
The other approaches
that were done before,
they were limited
to linear systems.
But now when you treat it
as a game,
from a different viewpoint,
you could suddenly,
you could suddently tackle
nonlinear problems
you couldn't do before.
So that was a little
bit about the past.
And I didn't dare to go f-more
than to roughly 1980
because one of my colleagues who was a professor of history said,
"Never, ever talk
about recent things
because you'll never have
a good perspective on them."
So I was brave
when I went to 1980.
I didn't want to go any further.
So now I'll talk
about the present.
And, em, eh, about applications.
There are lots and lots and lots
of applications of control
in the traditional fields,
and this application
are expanding.
So we have it in power
systems, in process control,
in aerospace, in automotives,
in buildings and robotics.
We have it in computer systems.
We have it also at other levels.
For example, in global
enterprise control.
You have it in advertisement.
You have it in
mobile telephones.
You have it in art and games,
and you have it in physics
and biology.
So not only the tra-traditional
fields are expanding
but also the application
fields are expanding.
I'll give ya, I'll give you
illustrations of this.
Here is, for example,
a process control example.
It's also something
I've been involved with.
A simple way to tune
simple controllers.
So there's a PID controller
that you would like to tune,
what you do is set
the switch in a relay here.
Then you get like a thermostat.
And what happens
with a thermostat,
the tempers starts to oscillate, start to swing.
Well, the swinging there
contains useful information,
so by analyzing the swinging you
can pick up enough information
to tune a PID controller
and then you can just switch it, switch it over.
It's a robust and easy to use.
It's well adapted to users.
You can just have a button
that you push,
and it's done by quite a large company, at the time,
so there are hundreds of thousands of,
of these sort of devices
out there today.
I-I gave you a nice
example of this.
This comes from, em, em,
a paper mill
up in Naven, Sweden.
And, em, eh, I wasn't
there myself, so I,
this is second-hand story.
So my-my colleagues
were up there.
They had been a student of
these controllers
with automatic tuning.
And typical commission a factory
is something that typically takes a week or two.
Y-y'know, you have to
fix up the instruments.
You have to
tune controllers, etc.
In this case they did it
in three days.
So what they did, they make, uh, sure the instruments right.
Connect one of these
autotunes and push a button.
This loop is clear.
Go to the other loop.
So people were very
happy about this.
So they said, well can't you use this magic device
on this beast of process
we have here
that we have not really
been able to control.
And this was a destination tower
and I'll show you here what's happening.
Eh, time is running this way.
It's one of these old
fashioned instruments.
You see here it's oscillating.
And this is run under,
under PID control.
Eh, well here, uthm,
what is this?
This is, ah,
roughly before launch.
You put it,
control into manual
and then
the oscillation stopped.
Here at 2 o'clock
in the afternoon
they push the tuning button.
They push a button.
So now what-what's
happening here,
you have, essentially,
the relay feedback.
Here, in the beginning,
you are just measuring a little bit of noise and hysteresis
and then you can see it's not in a perfect sinusoidal iteration
but it's enough to pick out
the dynamics.
And of course here people
are starting to get worried.
It doesn't work.
And in there the controller has
figured out by itself
that now I know what parameters are and I can regulate,
and then see how well
it regulates.
And this takes from 2:00 in the
afternoon 'til,
what is it here?
Eh, it's, uh, 7:00 o'clock
in the evening.
So, it's a long time,
but, eh,it tuned successfully.
So I think this is a nice little
example of automatic tuning.
Here's a very different example.
This is a comp-ehh,
it's a factory complex.
Eh, again, a paper factory.
You have lots
of manufacturing units
and then you have
storage tanks, etc.
And here the problem is to run the whole factory in a, in, eh,
a sensible way.
Eh, this is work that
was done by ABB.
And what they do is that they've
been doing mathematic
and model of the whole thing.
The model is partic-complicate.
It's about, er, a few
thousand variables.
So what they do is that they
estimate the state from sensors.
Then they run an optimization
program, and then they simulate.
And at this stage
they give commands to the people
who are running
the different units
about how they are going to chan-change production settings.
Some of the production settings
are set there automatically.
So it's an example of, em, automation
of-of a more complex systems.
Em, this then grew up.
This would be typical
process control.
This would be the manufacturing
system I was talking about.
What's happening now is control
is now creeping up together
with the business systems.
Em, so, for example, Wal-Mart is
one of the companies
who's most skilled at dealing with this higher level here
to keep, y'know, storage of things like this, um,
at a low level.
Here's another example that
comes from General Electric.
Eh, it's what's called
a trip optimizer.
It has to do with how you should
run freight trains effectively.
Eh, and the trick
to run freight trains
is that you should try to,
you should arrive
in the right time
and you should avoid braking
as much as possible.
So what General Electric
has done
is that they have applied optimal control
and then they have made a nice implementation of a system.
So, they are using
wireless links,
eh, s-so, to on board computers so you can know what you are.
There are maps, you know
what the terrain looks like.
So if you are going
to go up a hill
you can go a little bit faster.
When you go down, etc.
You shouldn't brake
when you go down.
And then they have done an
integrated system like this
that is run by
the train operators.
So this system is now, eh,
in commercial operation.
In automotive, I think that
deserves a special slide
because automotive is a strong
technology driver.
Y'know, there are so many cars
and the car companies
are so powerful
so they can get, em, CMI manufacturing companies
to do things they may not
otherwise be willing to do.
So for example, eh, eh, they persuaded Intel and Motorola
to do the micro controller.
In other words, eh, eh,
it's a computer with built-in
A to D and D to A.
And also, right now, eh, the automotive industry's pushing
the sensory industry, very much
so we are getting
cheap accelerometers
and cheap gyroscopes.
And, em, i-i-it
started with them,
engine control, because it was impossible to satisfy
the California emission standard
without, with-with
tradition means.
So the only way to do this
was to introduce feedback.
So that's what's happened.
And then once you started to get
a computer into the car,
there were many opportunities
to many other things.
So then you, one,
got cruise control.
You got adaptive cruise control.
Today you get
collision avoidance
and you get traction control.
And you get also
line gade-guided assistance.
And also one is moving
to traffic flow control.
There was a very interesting
project run at, uh,
by University of Berkeley
on platooning of cars.
Em, you wanted to, eh, get more
throughput on the highway
by shortening the distances between cars
and then you were going to run them automatically with about,
y'know, half a meter
between them
and then you can push through cars very quickly.
You can say it's a way
of making trains out of cars,
but it was
an interesting project.
Now here's, em, eh, another one of this namely for, for, trucks.
This is done by Scania, which
is a Swedish car company, KTH.
So by running trucks
close to each other, here,
you can reduce a lot of the,
a-air resistance between them.
And in a modern k-t-car today there are about 80,
you could say there's
about 80 control systems
or 80, eh, microprocessors.
And the way the automotive
industry deals with complexity
is that, they buy
the whole system.
They buy the sensor.
They buy the actuator.
They buy the computer.
And that was all right if
you had, em, handful of systems.
Eh, now when you're getting
80 of them
where some of them may use the same sensory information
it's getting more complicated.
So now there's a very strong
push in the automotive industry
to get an infrastructure
where they can do this.
There's also a problem about
specifications
because typical
specifications here,
you write a little book in English about half an inch thick
and they hand this to some of the manufacturers
and say, okay,
this is what I want.
And then they send you
an electronic book
and say here it is.
So the question is,
how do you verify this?
And how do you make
sure that it works?
And of course it
doesn't always work.
So this is one of the areas
where there's a tremendous need
for systematic procedures.
Em, here's another example.
Eh, it's, em, automotive
powertrain control.
Eh, and it's a nice system
done by Honeywell
which are selling
to car manufacturers
so that the car manufacturers can introduce
optimizing control into cars.
Eh, I think I'm going
to skip this one.
Eh, also, mobile telephones.
I think this is
really interesting.
Em, here is an example of a
mobile telephone in the 1980s.
You see price.
Eh, very expensive.
And you take one today,
about 13 dollars.
The weight, 4 kilograms.
Now it's 60 kilograms.
And if you look to the control
loops, there are about 10,
10 critical control loops
in a phone.
And then you multiply by
the number of phones per year.
So, i-in the mobile industry is actually leading
in terms of number
of control loops.
So this is the number
of control loops you have
in mobile telephones per year.
So they require some attention.
You do frequency control.
Em, you do power control
and gain control.
And mostly it's fairly
simple controls,
but you had to pay careful attention to them
because you manufacture
so many of them.
There are actually 6,000 people
who work in mobile
telephone technology
right next to our university
which is kind of interesting
for us.
Em, here's another area,
which I think, should be
of prime importance
for this campus.
You're going to get this
super computer coming here.
Uh, this super computer is
generating a lot of heat.
That you have to get, you have to buy the electricity for it
and then you have to
supply the heating.
So, control of computing centers
is becoming very important.
And it's both a matter of
allocating the resources.
Eh, you have a lot of jobs coming into the, the cloud
and then you have to
allocate the resources
in the computer system to deal with this in an efficient way.
You also have to have
to manage energy.
And typically in the system you
can lower the voltage by,
thereby, y'know,
reducing the clock speed
and you're reducing,
you're reducing power consumption energy.
They're quite interesting
control problems to do this.
And you're certainly going to
get one of these problems,
here, on campus,
which could be a very interesting test case.
So they said the same thing about data management
in computing centers.
Here's a somewhat
unexpected things.
It is about
internet advertising.
Eh, o-one nice thing about the
internet is that, uh,
uh, the idea is,
how should you design,
er, an advertisement campaign.
Y'know, you're putting in
money to do this and this
and that and you are expecting
a certain outcome.
Eh, a nice thing about
the internet is that
it's very easy to measure
the outcome quickly.
Em, and, em, there is a company
called Advertisement.Inc, originally.
It was founded by a son
of Leuenberger who is
one of our community.
It's, eh, out in Palo Alto.
And they are doing
systems like this.
So they are doing systems
to, essentially,
automate a use optimization for inter-internet advertisement
and they are using the sort of typical tools that we have,
y'know, modeling
and feedback control.
Then I have to talk about
art and games,
and I, this slide
is sort of violent.
It's done by young people.
So I have to, I had to stop.
Y'know, they can look at
many things at the same time.
I would, would like you
to look at this.
Em, this is done
by Raff D'Andrea,
eh, who was at Cornell who is now professor at the ETH
and, em, this is what he calls The Chair.
It starts like this
and then,
eh, it falls down
and then it starts over again.
This is in a museum in Toronto.
Eh, he has also done
other things.
So this is a, eh, a,
a nice piece of art.
Here's another one.
I know there are people here who
are interested in quadrocopters.
So these are quadrocopters
in Switzerland.
You see there roughly
what they look like.
And they are building pyramids.
And of course this stones are
lighter than what
the Egyptians had,
[laughing]
eh, but they certainly
build quicker.
So I think it's
interesting to see
that control is now moving into the, the art world.
And, em, Raff D'Andrea was also,
I-I'm going to stop this one.
You are, not like
my grandchildren
because they all fall
at the same time.
Eh, he also participated very
successful in the RoboCup
where little robots were
playing soccer together.
So, y'know, they are
running around there
and trying to beat
the other team.
Eh, I think Raff D'Andrea
won the World Cup twice
or something like this.
Eh, but this is not only games.
The same team have done this
with the same type
of technology.
It's about, em, eh,
doing warehouses.
For example, when Amazon is
going to package books
and send them to you.
And what they have done
is that by using feedback,
they have been able to use
very simple devices
and then they are using feedback
to make very accurate
motion based on this.
So they are, they are using
the feedback,
feedback tricks and, em, eh,
they are not only
playing games like this,
they're also doing real things that are now making profit.
Eh, this is called Kiva Systems
and I think the company
has now been bought by Amazon.
Now, The Chair was in the
National Gallery of Canada,
so I think it's nice that control has made its,
made its mark there.
Em, well, control has also
had impact in physics.
And there are two people who
have got the Nobel Prize
in physics for control effort.
The first one was a Swedish
engineer called Gustaf Dalen,
who invented the switch
for lighthouses.
Y'know, lighthouses,
when it's dark, you want to switch the switch on,
and when it's light,
you will switch it off.
And he had a very simple idea.
He was using,
three polished metal bars
and one black metal bar.
When, eh, light is shining,
y'know, the, em, the-the black one e-expands
and then it was open like this
and it revolutionized lighthouses all over the world.
The second one is a Dutch
engineer, Simon van der Meer,
who was working with
this accelerators
where you are sending
particles around a circuit
and he invented something called stochastic cooling.
There're some in-very interesting effects
done right now in quantum
and molecular systems.
And on here I have to mention
this one, too, about,
y'know, I think I'm doing, almost great with time,
I think, yeah.
Eh, y'know, turbulence has always been a challenge
in physics
to explain turbulence.
And, eh, i-it's governed
by Navier-Stokes equations.
A nonlinear partial
differential equations.
And then people
a long time ago,
they linearized
the Navier-Stokes equations
around, eh, eh, eh,
some behavior
and then they analyzed
how will the eigenvalues of the linearized motion behave
when you're changing
Reynolds number.
They found it was
never unstable.
So they couldn't
explain it like this.
So, the rumor went along that you can never explain turbulence
by linear theory.
But then, eh, a couple of control theorists, eh,
Mohammed Dahleh, who is no longer with us, unfortunately,
and Bassam Bamieh
They did the following.
They analyzed,
if you have perturbations
in the world,
how do these perturbations propagate to the velocity field?
And they linearized
this operator.
And then they were analyzing
the gain of that operator.
I mean, how much
of the variations here
propagated into the flow.
And they got very nice
agreement with, eh,
how turbulence changes with Reynolds numbers.
So I think that's one, one, one area where system theory
have contributed to, y'know, classical physics problem.
Then in-in physics, eh, you use feedback in the large scales
for adaptive optics.
What you're essentially doing
there, is that,
you're reducing the variation that happens
when the rate is going through the atmosphere
and the speed of light
is changing in the atmosphere.
You get rid of this by feedback.
The other area here is, uh, is, uh, in the nano scale.
We're using atomic
force microscope
to essentially, look at
surfaces in very details.
And of course both systems
depend very critically on
efficient feedback systems.
If you do, for example, a
better feedback system here,
the biologists are
looking at samples.
Could see a picture, y'know, five times faster
than they can look before,
for example.
Up here you can get
much sharper images.
Very clear what
control would do here.
Biology's an interesting one.
Since I'm not a biologist,
em, I-here's a book called
The Way Life Works
and it has seven chapters
and, eh, one chapter
is about feedback.
And this is a quote
from the book.
"That feedback is a central
feature of life.
"The process of feedback governs
how we grow,
"respond to stress
and challenge,
"and regulate body temperature,
"blood pressure,
cholesterol level.
"The mechanisms operate
at every level,
"from the interaction
of proteins to-to organisms."
So that's taken bonafide
from this book.
And, y'know, right now,
there's a lot of activity
in systems biology
and related fields.
One tries to merge this.
I personally think it's a
difficult thing to do,
eh, but, em, it's certainly
a very worthwhile effort.
So that was a little
bit about the present.
Now, what about the future?
I think we have some interesting
challenges because, em,
we are now starting to deal
with complex networked systems.
You can think about the
internet itself, for example.
You can think about
power systems.
You can think about, what you're
talking about smart grids.
When you're gonna, y'know,
to, to charge electric cars.
You're going to use
electric cars for storage.
You're going to generate
electricity in the houses, etc.
We're also getting system
that are called sensor
and actuator rich.
If you take a camera,
y'know, camera with,
say ten me-megapixels.
Eh, if you then view this
as a sensor,
it is a sensor which has
a lot of information in it.
And I would say that the systems
we have now in control,
they can easily deal with, say,
20-100 variables, 20-100 variables can deal with well.
When we're coming into this,
we need to think about systems in a very different way.
And what's going to happen is
that we are to break up
the system.
It's no longer sufficient
to have the central Kalman filter that sits there
and do everything.
We have to have local
feedback in the sensors.
We-if we have,
for example, images
we have to do a lot of work in the images themselves
to pick out
the relevant information.
And this is a
tremendous ch-challenge.
Another thing that's
popping up here
is safe design
of embedded system.
I mentioned this
problem about the car.
When it's specified something by
a book in English,
it's not easy to verify
what you get this right.
So this is
a tremendous challenge
that we have not solved.
Another one is autonomy,
and to do autonomy you need to do adaptation, learning,
reasoning, cognition, etc.
And then we have
the applications
throughout the field,
so I will elaborate
a little bit about this.
This is a picture I got
from a friend of mine,
eh, at, em,
Wright-Patterson Air Force Base.
It tells about Flight Control, An Evolution of Automation
to Enable Greater
Air Vehicle Capability.
And you see what they're
striving for
is that they are striving for
a higher degree of autonomy.
So they would like to have, y'know, vehicles that are
much more autonomous
than they are before.
The same thing is happening
out there in space.
And, um, em, adaptive control can play a small part of this
but we have to bring in
elements of learning
and cognition in here
which are,
not so easy to do
if you're going
to do it autonomously.
There have been
some interesting
things done, though.
Most of you have probably heard
about the Darpa Urban Challenge.
Y'know, when you drive car
on an air force bay
out in California,
they should obey the California driving rules.
And th-you mix them up
with other cars
that are driving around.
And, eh, there were a handful
of cars,
who were
fulfilling of the specification.
Um, among them was this car
here that was the winning car.
And they have some elements
of adaptation, learning,
and connection.
They have to have
a lot of safety.
They have to have diagnostics.
If you're going to have
real systems,
you also have to think about maintenance and reconfiguration.
I should mention, though,
at that already 1995,
y'know, that's long time ago,
17 years ago,
a German researcher
named Dickmanns
was running a Mercedes Benz
from Munich to Copenhagen
on the German Autobahn
and, eh, they had an autonomous car with a lot of sensors on it.
And of course the driver on the
Autobahn, they had to sit there
and also supervise it manually.
And they recorded whenever they
have to do manual interaction.
But they could run 95%
autonomously already in 1995,
which I think is
quite remarkable.
Eh, so my feeling is that, eh, and this is very subjective,
that I think we are
moving into third phase.
Like I said, the second phase
was driven by the space race
and by computers.
Now we're driven by complex
networked systems
and applications in physics
and biology.
So these are some
very strong drivers.
And, eh, some things
we have to have there.
We have to have autonomy.
We have to learn
to deal with sensor
and actuator rich systems.
We have to learn how to do
provable safe design
and reconfiguration.
Now when you have the cars
with a lot of computers in,
when you drive them in
and you have to make a change
of them, something,
you must have a safe way
to introduce changes
in the system effectively.
And I also think as control
engineers what we have to do
is that we have to recover
the holistic view.
Eh, I think what happened in
the 60s wasn't necessary
because if you're going to develop, y'know,
new areas and new field,
there is no way
but to dive into it,
y'know, forget about the rest.
Dive into it an-and develop
the mathematics.
And we still have to do this
in many of this field,
but to serve the engineering world that's sitting out there,
we must also have people who have a holistic view of things
and that's a major challenge
that I will talk
a little bit about.
And, eh, if you take this NIH study, The Engineer of 2020,
this is precisely
what they are saying.
That, eh, contemporary challenges, er,
require a systems perspective.
So we must make sure that we're
getting students
with a broad
systems perspective.
I'm very pleased to see
John Barris here.
So, uh, he's been advocating this for a very long time.
In my view it is
something like this.
I'm pretentious enough to
put control in the middle.
Doesn't matter
what you put it.
[laughing]
Eh, then we have
to have computing.
We have to have communication.
We have to mathematics.
And out here we
have the real world.
And to do the system we're
talking about
you must in some way grasp
aspects of all of this.
Now, it's impossible
for a single person
to be good at all of this.
But what we can do
is I'm sure we can
educate, eh, students
who are very good at
one of these fields
and who know enough about
these interfaces in here
so that they can communicate
and work effectively
with the other specialists
that are sitting here.
And then, of course,
we need to have some
overall people in here.
Em, eh, eh, I talk about some,
for example, I think this, this interface is real easy,
control and communication,
because in my mind it's essentially the same stuff.
But it's taught in different
departments by different people,
which I think is ridiculous.
Eh, Mathematics is the same.
There is a couple
of differences.
Communication, the guys don't bother about time delays
and we control guys
are worried about time delays.
But I think these
are minor things.
So I think we can do a lot
both in terms of courses
and other things
t-to merge these kinds
of things together.
Eh, I'm gonna talk a little
more about s-something.
This is the easy interface.
It only has to do with
university politics.
[laughing]
But now you have a young,
vigorous chancellor here,
so, I think, uh, you may have
a chance to do something.
Eh, I will talk about the
computer science barrier.
Y'know, here you have control
and here you have computing.
Incidentally, I borrowed this
from Bruce Krogh at,
eh, Carnegie Mellon.
So what control engineers do,
they work with
stability feedback,
ordinary differential equation, moderate complexity,
and worry about robustness.
And then they write a-a Simulink simulation.
They throw this over
to the computing guys.
And they know about
languages, etc,
formal methods,
abstraction, architecture.
And then they take the
simulating program
and then they do some kind
of software for it.
And, eh, sometimes it works.
Sometimes it doesn't work.
So what's happening here,
control engineers have to know
a little bit more
about computing.
Computing engineers have
to know more about control.
I'll give you one example.
In automotive now there is a
communications device
called the can bus which is a standard communication
protocol in the cars.
It's a beautiful
little protocol,
but it has one drawback.
It has time delays,
and not only that,
it has very big time delays.
And if I said that time delays
are bad for control system,
very big time delays
are really bad.
So if this person who did
the can bus
had had a good introductory course in control,
I said just an introductory course in control,
that was good.
He would have known,
time delays are bad.
So this would not be.
a good thing
if you're gonna close
control loops.
It's alright
if you're gonna just
raise your windows up and down,
but if you're going to close
control feedback loops around there, it's not a good idea.
So that's one example,
that could have been
prohibited by good education.
[laughing]
I should also mention computing.
And I still remember,
eh, well you can start with Vannevar Bush.
He said, "Engineering can
progress no faster
"than mathematical analysis
on which it's based.
"Formal mathematics
is frequently inadequate.
"A mechanical solution offers the most promise."
He was at MIT and then
he went ahead and built
The Mechanical
Differential Analyzer,
that could solve about six ordinary differential equations.
I worked for IBM research,
and my boss,
I was in the math department
for a while,
my boss was Herman Goldstine.
He built the first computer
together with John von Neumann.
So, he was chair
in the math department.
At one staff meeting
he said this,
which I've never forgotten.
"When things change
by two orders of magnitude
"it is not evolution,
it is revolution."
Now you combine this
with Moore's Law,
you get a revolution
every ten years.
[laughing]
So, you recognize that
computing power
changes by two orders
of magnitude roughly speaking
every ten years.
And that's why I have to
exchange laptops
every third year, for example.
And, eh, there's a
tremendous potential.
If you think about this, y'know,
that you're gaining two orders of magnitude per ten years,
so there's
a f-fantastic potential.
But we have not been able
to capitalize on this
in engineering productivity.
And I think that is something
to think about
because there is
something out there
that we could probably do something about.
I should also mention that what I call the physics barrier,
y'know.
Here is, we have the real world.
And there we have
mass, energy, momentum
and up here we have control.
And I said before
that block diagrams
is very useful for control
because that was what w-people used to discover that autopilots
was the same as process control.
The block diagrams
look the same.
But we as control engineers have
been brainwashing students
with block diagrams,
over 50 years,
but, and we use them
for physical modeling,
but block diagrams are absolutely worthless
for phy-serious
physical modeling
because in blocks you have a causal connection.
You have an input
and you have an output.
When it connect
two physical systems
you have
bidirectional interaction
and that is not captured
by block diagrams.
So, so please,
if you're educate
in control engineer
say that there's something more than block diagrams, okay?
Eh,then I'll talk about
modeling and simulation.
Again, a quote from this,
The Engineer of 2020
where they say that
"computer-based design-build
engineerer will become the norm
"for most product designs,
"accelerating the creation
of complex structure
"for which multiple subsystems combine to form a product."
So in other words, y'know, modeling is simulation.
And so this is not my world.
I said, most were personal.
This is from a more
authoritative source than me.
I'll give you a nice
example of this.
Eh, the major German
car manufacturers,
I listed them here,
and their suppliers,
have standardized
when it comes to doing
climate control systems in cars.
You know climate control, it has, um, compressors,
it has heating changes,
it has pumps, etc.
And what they have done,
is that the supplier,
who supplies a hardware piece
of hardware,
he also delivers a validated mathematical model of that.
Happens to be in a
language called Modelica.
And then the car companies,
they are taking then this model,
eh, so they say, well,
uh, maybe this
p-company here has a cheaper version of a compressor,
should I use it?
So then they take the-the model from-from this company,
they put it into their simulator and they run the typical, eh,
European standard drive cycle
and then they figure out what happens to power consumption,
to gasoline consumption,
what happens to quality,
no big deal,
so then we can buy
the cheaper one.
So I think this is a very nice
illustration of, em,
how you can use models.
In this case,
the IP is protected by
extensive en-en-encryptation
and the substantial reduction here is in-in road
and climate chamber testing.
And I'm very proud to say that
this was done by,
eh, some of my grad students
who also have this company Modelon, who is doing this.
Eh, actually the same technology was used by Toyota
when they made the Prius.
And the software
was also done
by one of my former
PhD students.
Toyota had, at the time,
300 engineers working with
mo-with working with
what's now called Modelica.
Ok, now come to
the educational challenges.
Eh, we have to educate the engineers who can deal with this
in the future.
We also have to educate
people in physics and biology.
And last year I actually gave
a course in control
to physicists,
based on the request from
the physics department,
which was kind of fun.
Em, and I think in control we have, what I call the dilemma
of emerging fields.
Y'know, I said control
is a very young field,
literal 50 years.
So what did we do?
Well, we taught
everything we knew.
That was, first course.
When we knew a little bit more, we made a new course.
And then we made a new course,
and we made a new course,
and we made a new course.
And right now there are
simply too many courses,
eh, because if we're going
to have these people
who are well rounded
and well educated
we can't have them to do 15 courses in control or,
I don't know what it is here,
to get a PhD in Urbana.
We can't have them to, because,
they also have to learn a little bit about communication,
about computer science,
and about, about physics.
So we have to do
something about this.
And the way to do this,
I think,
is to filter out
the fundamentals,
to compress, eh, to compress,
figure out, what are really
the important things?
What are the essentials here?
And we have to do this at
the courses to all the level.
It's a lot of work.
Particularly if you have
your courses developed
and are going to teach it.
But I think in the long run it's
going to be very worthwhile.
I also mentioned here computing.
And I think computers
have changed
what we mean by
a solution to a problem.
Y'know, in the old time
you had a solution
if you can write it down
with sine functions
or something like this.
And now, t-for example,
if something reduces to a-a linear algebra problem,
it's essentially solved.
If something reduces to an
ordinary differential equation with constant coefficient,
it's also solved because
we can generate everything
we know with computers.
So I think, erh, by thinking
intelligent about this,
I think we can do this.
And what we need is,
that we have to have students
who have very deep knowledge
in specific areas
but who are reasonably broad
in neighboring areas
and also, who are able
to communicate
and also, to work in teams.
This is what we need
in order to do this.
So now, eh, what I've done,
I've spoken about introduction, past, present, and future.
And now let me try to summarize.
Eh, I think, personally, control
is a very vital dynamic field.
And if we watch out
for the foundations
and if we think about telling other people what we are doing,
eh, I think we are going
to continue to do great.
Eh, there are lots
of applications
in traditional fields,
so engineers we're
educating here,
they can find lots of job
out in the industry.
Now we have, also have to deal with networked embedded systems.
We have to deal with
autonomy and safety.
And I think we should take
the educational challenge
here seriously.
We were discussing here during
dinner, for example,
that there are many changing modes of education right now
and I think this may be some vehicle we can jump on
to, to do this.
Eh, so, what we should do,
is that we should continue to take care of the foundations
and then to develop
the holistic view.
If we do this, control will
also be great in the future.
Thank you very much.
[applause]
(man)
Thank you, Karl,
for this inspiring, eh, lecture.
I think we can take, eh, eh,
a couple of questions
from the audience.
When you have a big crowd it's
(Karl)
They are like Swedish students.
(man)
Yes, that's right.
Yes.
(Karl)
John, John Barras
(inaudible audience)
(Karl)
Ah, eh, co-could you,
could you repeat, eh,
they wanted
(inaudible audience)
(Karl)
Yeah
(inaudible audience)
(Karl)
I-I will repeat,
I will repeat the question.
Eh, t-the question was that
before we had
a very simple situation.
We had the sensor
and an actuator
and then we had the controller sitting between
and maybe you had ten sensors and ten actuators,
but you have a block sitting there in between.
And John asked, what is happening right now
when we have networked systems.
And I'm trying here,
to pick up a little picture,
as an illustration.
Eh, ah,
Eh, I'll do it here.
Eh, it should be,
uh, I think it was
somewhere down here.
Oh, I think I'll skip
the picture.
Eh, I think this will require
new paradigms.
I mean, will we require, y'know.
My view is this.
That I think it will
requi-require
total different way
of thinking.
So, so what you have to do is that you have, eh, eh,
you have to have a lot of, eh, eh-eh, well, to be honest,
I don't really know
what the solution is,
but clearly it requires a very different way of thinking
than when you had, for example, ten sensors and ten actuators
and then, y'know, some kind of computing box in the middle.
So, so that's why I'm saying,
y'know, that
control is by no means dead, y'know.
We have these problems,
that are very challenging,
which are sitting out there that we have to deal with
where we don't know
the solution.
And that's, of course, great
if your graduate student are looking for good problems.
And it's not going to be easy.
(inaudible audience)
(Karl)
Yeah.
Uh, so, eh, th-the comment was that, eh, eh,
if you, if you have
information theory,
you have the problem
bringing the information out
to the network.
So, tha-that's also a problem.
So,
yes.
I think, you know, eh,
Both John and I
will be out here,
eh, so you can, you can,
you can corner John, then me
to talk more about this
later on, so.
(inaudible)
(Karl)
No, no.
(man)
Well, thank you Karl.
[applause]
(Karl)
Thank you.